Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 12 -- Letters from Franklin 1733-1789 Mss.B.F85inventory12
American Philosophical Society
- Letters from Benjamin Franklin
  - to Ralph Izard., 1778 March 10; A. Dr. by Benjamin Franklin of L. 1p.; The American Commissioners?, Passy
    As soon as any treaties are completed, and it is in their power to do so, will comply with his request; they will be happy to confer with him at his pleasure.
  - to [Arthur Lee]., 1778 March 17; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Has not made use of the offer of Mr. Beaumann, of Bordeaux, to carry his despatches, now knowing what confidence may be placed in the Captains of their packets. Concerning bills drawn by Congress on the Commissioners.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 248; Bigelow, VI, 145; Smyth, VII, 121).
  - to Ralph Izard., 1778 March 30; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Will not give the man the pass to Italy. Prevented giving Mr. Izard the satisfaction he wishes, by much and very important business; reasons why Mr. Izard received no answer to his letter of the 5th inst. Condoles with him on the Charleston fire.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 250).
  - to [Arthur Lee]., 1778 April 1; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Reply to his charge of negligence or unfaithfulness. Settlement of the Commissioner's accounts.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 256; Bigelow, VI, 154; Smyth, VII, 129).
  - to A[rthur] Lee., 1778 April 3; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Reason for not answering some of his letters.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VII, 132).
  - to A[rthur] Lee., 1778 April 4; A. Dr. of L. 7p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    France has a right to send as Ministers whom it pleases, without their approbation. Mr. Lee's extraordinary conduct in regard to the personal intercourse of the Commissioners. Settlement of the accounts. Reply to the charge of being inconsistent with his duty to the public. Cause for not answering some of his letters.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 257; Bigelow, VI, 155; Smyth, VII, 132).
  - to [Arthur Lee]., 1778 April 6; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Regarding orders given to Mr. [Jonathan] Williams, Jr., for a large quantity of clothing; the discharge of drafts.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 265; Bigelow, VI, 162, Smyth, VII, 136).
  - to Sir James Jay., 1778 April 17,18; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Draft of three letters, resenting Jay's lack of confidence in the Commissioners.
  - to Comte de Vergennes., [1778.] May 6; A. Dr. of L. in 3d P. 1p.; Benjamin Franklin, Arthur Lee and John Adams. Passy
    Are extremely sensible of his good offices in obtaining the King's orders relating to the presentation of Mr. Adams to His Majesty. Will do themselves the honor of waiting on His Exellency on the day agreeable to his obliging invitation.
  - to M. and Mme. Lafreté., [1778.] May 9; A. Dr. of L. in 3d P. 1p.; Benjamin Franklin and John Adams. Passy
    Engaged for to-morrow and every other day next week; but will do themselves the honor of dining at Surêne on Monday the 18th, if convenient to them.
  - to [Arthur Lee]., 1778 May 17; A. Dr. of L. in 3d P. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    His reasons for not signing Mr. Lee's letter [XLV, 124b, page 511] to Mr. Grand the American banker.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 272; Bigelow, VI, 176; Smyth, VII, 154).
  - to [Ferdinand] Grand., 1778 May 17; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; The American Commissioners?, Passy
    Desiring Mr. Grand to accept no bills without the joint order of the Commissioners, and to forward to them all letters that come to him addressed to Mr. Deane.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 272, Note; Bigelow, VI, 176, Note I: Smyth, VII, 154, Note I).
  - to ----- Le Roy, Cherbourg., 1778 April 23 -1778 May; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Thinks the produce of Capt. [John] Burnell's prizes never came to their hands, but was paid to Mr. [Joshua] Johnson or to Mr. [William] Carmichael for Mr. Johnson who resides at Nantes and is concerned for the owners. Capt. Burnell should apply to Mr. Johnson.
  - to Capt. Sainneville., 1778 June 23; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Thanks him for the kind care of his letters and packets.
    Printed in works (Smyth VII, 163).
  - to A. Borel., 1778 June 24; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Objects to the proposed engraving on the score of its being too flattering; advises placing a senator in Roman dress in the picture instead of a portrait of himself [Franklin]; desires to have it dedicated to Congress and not to himself.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 June 24; 2p.; Borel, A
    The same.
    (In French by Jean Baptiste Le Roy.)
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 277; Bigelow, VI, 185; Smyth, VII, 163).
  - to Chevalier de Champigny., 1778 July 24; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Gave him two or three guineas for which he was to receive the History of England when written; received two volumes of that history, and four volumes of histories of Sweden and Denmark, which he never desired. Requests him to send his correspondent to receive back the six volumes of different histories.
  - to Mme. Brillon., [1778 July]; A. Dr. of L. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    To prove that she does not really love him, narrates the story of a Bishop who refused alms to a beggar but was willing to give him his blessing. Declares that although she is as rich as an Archbishop in all moral and Christian virtues she has refused him her love, so as not to have to sacrifice the smallest particle of her virtue.
    Printed in Puttam's Monthly, Dec., 1906, 31.
  - to W[illia]m Lee., 1778 August 13; A. Dr. of L. S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Is ready to deliver the trunk to him, but is unwilling to have any concern in the opening of it; or in examining or sorting the papers.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VII, 184).
  - to [Antoine Raymond Jean Gaulbert Gabriel] de Sartine., 1778 August 18; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Regarding the exchange of prisoners.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VII, 185).
  - to Comte de Vergennes., 1778 August 18; L. 1p.; The American Commissioners?, Passy
    By the 8th Article of the Treaty of Commerce His Majesty engaged to employ his good offices with the Emperor of Morocco and the other powers on the coast of Barbary to provide as fully as possible for the safety of the inhabitants of the United States and their vessels and effects against violence from the Barbary States. Heard that there are American vessels in Italy desiring to return home and that there are merchants in Italy desiring to enter American trade, but that an apprehension of danger from the Barbary States is a discouragement. Requests his attention to the matter.
    (Press copy.)
  - to ------ de Perygnon., 1778 September 10; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Answers to questions on the subject of marriage in Pennsylvania.
  - The Story of the Ephemera, 1778 September 20; Diss. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Another translation.
  - to Ferdinand Grand., 1778 October 14; A.L.S (Incomplete.) 2p. and Dr. of L.S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Obliged for being informed of Capt. [Gustavus] Cunningham's misconduct. Regulations of Congress respecting privateers.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 298; Bigelow, VI, 214; Smyth, VII, 190).
  - to Job Prince., 1778 November 20; Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Informs him that he may safely confide to W[illiam] T[emple] Franklin what he has to communicate to the Commissioners. Has received no account of his vessel or its destination, from Congress. Informs him that if he sends any prizes into the ports, to address them to one of the American Agents there.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VII, 201).
  - to ----- [Le] Baron., 1778 November 20; Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Thanks him for his readiness to serve Capt. [Job] Prince. His bills for moderate supplies will be honored. Recommends his grandson to his civilities.
  - to ------ [Le] Baron., 1778 November 21; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Acquaints him that a person in their confidence, as desired by Capt [Job] Prince, sets out for Dieppe with answers to his and the Captain's letters.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VII, 202).
  - to William Temple Franklin, Dieppe., 1778 November 26; A.L.S 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Believes the whole a piece of roguery; wants him to return to Passy.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VII, 203).
  - to Mrs. R. Parsons., [1778 November ]; A. Dr. of L.S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Denies having given her husband the least encouragement in his project of entering the American army; lent him fifteen guineas which he never repaid; refuses to extricate him from further difficulties. Commiserates her unhappy situation, and, as she says she has not a shilling, sends her a guinea.
  - to John Ross, 1778 November 5; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Relating to Mr. Thomas Morris's papers, and his desire to have nothing to do with them except to deliver them up at once, before witnesses.
  - to A. Sube, Laporte, and others., [1778. December.]; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Expressing thanks for the verses and a wish that the connection between France and Amercica may be everlasting.
  - to Madame, ------., [1778.]; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Should certainly pay the greatest respect to the recommendation of Madame [Noailles de la Fayette, but it is impossible for him to do what is desired for M. Rolandeau, formerly an officer in the American service. M. Rolandeau's conduct. Has been ordered by Congress to encourage no more officers to come over. Rejoices on the good news from their friends in America, and the reputation her particular friend acquired there.
  - to ----- -----., [1778.]; Dr. by Jean Baptiste Le Roy of L. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Discussion about electricity. Reply to a correspondent who had made some experiments with the Leyden jar and who differed with Franklin in his deductions. Explains the phenomena observed in his experiments with the Leyden jar.
  - to Mme. Brillon, [1780 December 10]; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Dec 1906, 314, also in Works (Smyth, X, 426).
    Will call to see her and try to go up her stairs if she is unable to come down. Enjoyed M. Brillons's visits to him during her illness and was much amused by his humorous stories. M. [Pere] Pagin called to see him yesterday and had the patience to listen to him playing an air on the harmonica. (in French.)
  - to Comte de Vergennes., [1779 Feb. 9]; A. Dr. by Le Ray de Chaumont of L. 2p.; American Commissioners
    With reference to a lawsuit over a vessel recaptured from the English by the American privateer "General Mifflin," Capt. [Daniel] McNeill, and brought into l'Orient as a prize. The French laws leaves no doubt as to the validity of Capt. McNeill's claim. Complains of the slowness of the Courts in deciding such cases.
  - Passport for A French Vessel., [1779 Feb. 14]; Dr. of D. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
  - Passport for A French Vessel, [1779 Feb. 14]; Dr. of D. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
  - Story of the Ephemera (or day flies)., 1778; Diss. Translation. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    In the form of a letter to Mme. Brillon with an explantory preface by the translator.
    Printed in Proc. of Amer. Phil.Soc., 1901, Vol. XL, 90, also in Works (Sparks, II, 177; Bigelow, VI, 237; Smyth, VII, 206).
  - to Ferdinand Grand, A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Relative to a complaint made against Capt. [Gustavus] Cunningham's conduct towards Spain. (First part missing.)
  - Memorandum., [1778 Nov. 3]; Dr. of Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Reply to a complaint made by the Spanish Government against [Gustavus] Cunningham for his actions in seizing Spanish trading vessels. Expresses regret at his conduct on the occasion referred to and promises to lay the complaint before Congress.
    (In French by Ferdinand Grand.)
  - to Mme. Brillon., [1778 Dec. 10-15]; L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Humorous description of Heaven and how Franklin intends to spend his time there. Will wait for Mme. Brillon's coming. Asks her not to renew her contract there with M. Brillon but to pledge her troth to him.
    Transcribed by Mme. Brillon from the original and corrected by her, with memorandum of corrections of French in Dr. Franklin's handwriting.
    Printed in Proc. of Amer. Philos. Soc., 1901, Vol, XL, 109, also in Putnam's Monthly, Nov., 1906, 167.
  - to Mme. Brillon., [1778.]; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Was very sorry not to have been able to call to see her yesterday evening. Makes a comparison to prove that he loves her "too much" and more than she loves him. (Part of letter written in an imitation of Mme. Brillon's handwriting.)
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Dec., 1906, 313.
  - to Mme. Brillon., [1778.]; Dr. of L. 4p; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Only sees one defect in her which consists in a kind of sentimental avariciousness or a deisre to restrict and monopolize all his affection and not allow him to bestow any of it on other charming women. She is wrong in thinking that his affection cannot be divided up amongst a number of persons without loss to herself. Maintains that esteem, admiration, respect and even affection may be extended to a number of objects. She has no right to complain, moreover, as she excludes everything material from their relations and only allows him a few polite kisses now and then, such as she might give to her young cousins. Thinks he would have more reason to complain of her harsh treatment of his affections. Does not wish to be at war with her and proposes that they sign a treaty of peace, Submits the preliminary articles for her considertation and consent.
  - On the Issue of Paper Money by Congress., Mem. (in the handwriting of Le Ray de Chaumont). 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    On the issue of paper money by Congress to the amount of one hundred millions. Simply a kind of loan with which to pay its debts that Congress was unable to do otherwise. The paper money will have to be redeemed, just as a loan, the Government will have the use of one hundred millions for a certain time without any interest charges. The paper money also promotes and helps the circulation of money in general.
  - Memorandum, [1779 C. Jan. 1]; A. Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Address of M. Fleuri(ot)[an] de Langle, formerly an officer in the French cavalry.
  - Certificates as to the Probity of Silas Deane in the Public Service., [1778.]; Dr. of D. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
  - to Ralph Izard., 1779 January 4; A. Dr. of L. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Financial affairs of the United States in Europe. Hopes he will not insist on their giving him farther credit with their banker. Thinks he should reimburse the sum they advanced to him.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 308; Bigelow, VI, 292; Smyth, VII, 216).
  - to Messrs. Sube and Laporte., 1779 January 12; Dr. by Jean Baptiste Le Roy of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Is pleased to meet so many partisans of his country in France. Read with pleasure the statutes of their Society and the verses addressed to him. Appreciates the honors received from the Society of the friends of America at Marseilles. Hopes the alliance between France and his country will endure forever and contribute to the prosperity of their city.
  - to Abbé Du Bois, Nancy., 1779 January 12; A. Dr. by Jean Baptiste Le Roy of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Thanks him for his letter and the ingenious fable in verse. Is not proficient enough in French to fully appreciate the fine qualities of the verse but thinks the idea of the fable excellent and well applied. Pleased to hear of so many partisans of his country in France.
  - to The Continental Congress, Committee of Foreign Affairs., 1779 January 15; A. Dr. of L. 5p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Money advanced to Ralph Izard and William Lee.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 310; Bigelow, VI, 294; Smyth, VII, 218).
  - to Ralph Izard., 1779 January 20; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    His promise, whether made in the presence or absence of witnesses, should be fulfilled; repeats his intention of sending a copy of the letter with some farther reasons in addition.
  - to John Adams., 1779 January 22; A. Dr. of L. in 3d P. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Requests him to forward all the public papers in his possession. Promises to keep them in order and to cheerfully furnish him with any papers he may have occassion for.
    E. Mr. Adams on receipt of this, put all the Public Papers in to the hands of W[illiam] T[emple] Franklin.
  - to Messrs. Horneca, Fizeaux and Co., 1779 February 9; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Requests them to replace the goods which were sent over to Congress by mistake, for the account of Mr. Simeon Deane, charging the Commissioners with the account; he also asks them to remit the remainder of the money belonging to the United States to Mr. Ferdinand Grand.
  - Diary., 1779 February 12 to March 2; A. Mem. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - to Patrick Henry, Governor of Virginia., 1779 February 26; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    On the subject of procuring military supplies for the State of Virginia. Mr. William Lee's conduct in the affair.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 320; Bigelow, VI, 317; Smyth, VII, 238).
  - to Jean de Neufville., 1779 February 28; L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Paris
    Present state of affairs does not permit him to begin negotiations for a loan of 1,500,000 florins. The attempt by the United States to get a loan in Holland last year was not successful. Fears another attempt would not meet with more success and might injure the credit of the United States. If he can, with his credit and good offices, first succeed in getting a sufficient number of subscribers, Dr. Franklin could sign and send the preliminary agreement proposed by M. de Chaumont.
    (In French.) Copy.
  - to Jean de Neufville., 1779 February 28; Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Draft, by M. de Chaumont, of previous letter and preliminary agreement of proposed loan.
  - to G. Anquetil Brutère., 1779 February; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Advises him to make his complaint to the Court of Admiralty of Massachusetts Bay to which the privateer belonged; offers to transmit any papers and proofs thither.
  - to [Augustin Badran] Riotto., 1779 March 4; A. Dr. of D.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
  - to the marquis de Lafayette., 1779 March 22; A.Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    On the method of harrassing England by sea.
    Printed in Works (Bigelow, VI, 339; Smyth, VII, 269).
  - to "The London Packet.", 1779 March 24; Dr. of D. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Passport for Mr. [Guillaume] Bousie's vessel, "The London Packet," Capt. Meriton, with letters relating thereto. (3 p.)
  - to ------ Aubry., 1779 March 14; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Lexeuil
    Has no orders to send over any physicians; America is open to all French people who desire to settle there, but they must pay their own expenses.
  - to Gioanni De Bernardi, 1779 April 1; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Turin
    Thanks him for his good will towrads America, but their laws and language being different from those with which he is acquainted, can neither advise nor encourage him to go thither.
  - to Samuel Marcel, 1779 April 1; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Berne
    The army is full; with a small captial he might succeed in commerce or agriculture. but his voyage thither must be at his own expense; is not authorized to promise any kind of establishment, office, or employment to new-comers; the advantages he will find there, without any additional inducements.
  - to Pièrre Bon de Corcelles., 1779 March 19; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Moudon
    The lands of Pennsylavania not yet granted all belong to the Proprietary, Mr. Penn; the price is £5 the hundred acres; enumerates the advantages which render a free gift or land unnecessary.
  - to John Rosseaux., 1779 March 14; A. Dr, of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    The business of selling prizes, distributing the shares and paying salaries, has never been in his hands; recommends him to write to Mr. [Jonathan] Williams, [Jr.], at Nantes, for information.
  - to George F. Norton., 1779 May 18; A. Dr. of D.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
  - to Sir Edward Newenham., 1779 May 26; A. Dr. of D. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
  - to Dr. [Edward] B[ancroft?], 1779 May 31; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Asks him to acquaint the people that have a mind to remove to America, that they may do so with great safety to themselves and effects. Tells him to state the advantages of living in America.
  - to ----- King., 1779 July 22; A. Dr. of D.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
  - to ----- -----: Invitation, before June; Printed N. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Blank invitation to dinner for Monday, July 5, to celebrate the Anniversary of the Declaration of Independence.
  - to ----- Rattier., 1779 August 5; Dr. by Le Ray de Chaumont, of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Cannot accept proposal made by four English prisoners of war to give their services to the United States as artillery or battery officers. It is always prudent to beware of such offers made by English soldiers.
  - to [Whom it May Conern]., 1779 August 8; Dr. of D.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Certifies that the accounts of John Ross have been audited by Messrs. Wharton and Bancroft, and recommends that the United States pay the balance owing. Accompanied by the auditing report of Sam[uel] Wharton and Ed[ward] Bancroft.
  - to marquis de Lafayette, 1779 August 24; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Sends him a sword in the name of the Congress.
  - to marquis de Lafayette., 1779 August 24; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    The same translated into French.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 380; Bigelow, VI, 436; Smyth, VII, 370).
  - Recommendation of a Georgia Lieutenant, 1779 August 31; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
  - to William Temple Franklin., 1779 August; A.N. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Requests him to send the sword by his servant, as Mme. Brillon desires to see it.
  - to Cyprian Sterry, John Smith, Jr., and the Brigantine "Hope.", 1779 September 24; A. Dr. of D. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
  - to Comte de Vergennes., 1779 September 26; L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Wishes he could write something positive to the Congress in regard to the supplies they have asked for. Congress will be placed in a state of uncertainty; and the disappointment will give great advantage to their enemies, external and internal.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 382; Bigelow, VI, 441; Smyth, VII, 376).
  - to Joseph Wharton's Vessels., 1779 October; Dr. of D. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
  - to Madame Brillon., 1779 November 10; A. Dr. of Diss. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    The story of the whistle.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, II, 180; Bigelow, VI, 239; Smyth, VII, 414).
  - La Belle et La Mauvaise Jambe., Passy. I vol. 410.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Broadside. 1p.
  - to Count de Vergennes., [1779 before March 2]; Dr. by Le Ray de Chaumont of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Points out that the effect of such long and unreasonable delays in deciding claims by American vessels for prizes retaken from the English will be to discourage offensive operations by American war vessels against the English in European waters. Cites the claim of Capt. [Daniel] McNeill, of the American privateer "General Mifflin," which has not yet been settled after a delay of seven months.
  - to Mme. Brillon., A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790